<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Latest News | CARS-CO2 project</title>
    <link>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Latest News</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/media/icon_hu903a68f77459690139586f35488807c0_418737_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Latest News</title>
      <link>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>IMA 2022 conference</title>
      <link>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2022-06-22-ima-2022-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2022-06-22-ima-2022-conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Good news! First results of CARS-CO2 project will be presented at IMA2022 conference in Lyon (France).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk is entitled &lt;strong&gt;Monitoring CaSO4 carbonation with in situ Raman spectroscopy to study CO2 sequestration&lt;/strong&gt; (by &lt;em&gt;Carlos Pimentel&lt;/em&gt;, Germán Montes-Hernández, Alexander E.S. Van Driessche). I will present the results on Wednesday 20th at 12:30 in the session of &lt;em&gt;Mineral-Fluid interactions&lt;/em&gt;. The abstract will be shared after publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the information about the conference can be found in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ima2022.fr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IMA2022 webpage&lt;/a&gt;. The scientific program can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://ima2022.process.y-congress.com/ScientificProcess/schedule/?setLng=en#&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project abstract</title>
      <link>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2022-02-01-project-abstract/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2022-02-01-project-abstract/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the CARS-CO2 project webpage. If you want to know what the objectives of this project are, you can read the project summary below. The results of the research will be presented in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CARS-CO2 is a multidisciplinary project that is centred on the carbonatation of sulphates to establish a novel route to capture and store atmospheric CO2. The two main objectives of this project are: (i) improve our understanding of the crystallization process of sulphates and carbonates at mild hydrothermal conditions, and (ii) study the mechanism, kinetics and stability of the carbonatation of sulphates. Both objectives are paramount to accomplish our foremost goal, which is to evaluate the potential of sulphate carbonatation as a “sequestrator” of CO2. To achieve this, several state-of-the-art laboratory and synchrotron-based scattering techniques will be used to monitor in situ the mineral formation and transformation reactions. To complement the body of bulk mineralization data, during a secondment, isotopic fingerprinting will be used to determine the role of magnesium in the transformation reaction and to define if the transformation is solid state or solution mediated. The results obtained in this project will not only shed light on how CaSO4-based (waste) materials can help to reduce CO2 in the atmosphere but will also further unveil the formation mechanisms of sulphates and carbonates for relevant environmental conditions on Earth and Mars.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
