<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Latest News | CARS-CO2 project</title>
    <link>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Latest News</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/media/icon_hu903a68f77459690139586f35488807c0_418737_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Latest News</title>
      <link>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>This is the end... or not!</title>
      <link>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2024-04-17-this-is-the-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2024-04-17-this-is-the-end/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sadly, this MSCA project ended on 31 January 2024. On the 5th of February I started as an assistant professor at Universidad Complutense de Madrid, teaching Geology to the students of the Chemistry degree. In addition to preparing the classes I had to prepare the final report for the EU. Now that the course is almost finished and I have finished the review of the comments made by the EU on my report I have time to update this website with the latest progress I have made on the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January, we finally published a paper corresponding to the first work package I had proposed in the project, i.e. on the study of sulphate and carbonate minerals formation and, specifically, on bassanite formation. In this paper, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/publication/stawski-bassanite-2024/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;which is available in open access&lt;/a&gt;, we have managed to synthesise bassanite at temperatures below 100C. And why is this breakthrough important?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bassanite, CaSO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; ½H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O, is a sulphate widely used in construction, because when mixed with water it dissolves to recrystallise in the form of gypsum crystals, generating a resistant material that is present in our homes, as it is a fundamental component of plasterboard. Currently, the synthesis of bassanite is done by heating the gypsum at high temperatures (&amp;gt; 150 °C). Heating the gypsum to such high temperatures consumes a lot of energy and therefore also emits CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this work, we have used very saline solutions equilibrated with gypsum seeds (i.e. small gypsum crystals in suspension). These suspensions, kept under stirring and heated to 90 °C, yielded bassanite in a few minutes, which proved to be stable in suspension for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./graphicalabstract.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Graphical abstract of the paper. A time vs. temperature graph shows how gypsum rapidly converts to bassanite as the temperature increases. Drawings of the structures of these minerals and a drawing of the synchrotron experiment are included.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;Graphical abstract of the paper. It can be seen a time vs. temperature graph showing how gypsum rapidly converts to bassanite as the temperature increases. (Source: Stawski et al., 2024)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the methods we have used to monitor the evolution of these reactions is in situ Raman, which is available at ISTerre. I have specialised in this method during my two-year contract in France. Thanks to in situ Raman, we were able to observe minute by minute, by the changes in the Raman signal, how the gypsum dissolved in the solution to give rise to the crystallisation of the bassanite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To finish with this entry, which will not be the last, it only remains for me to mention that we are currently working on two more papers, one of them under review focused on the formation of gypsum and the other one focused on the carbonation of sulphate minerals to capture CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (which has been the research on which work packages 2 and 3 of the project have focused). When these papers are published, I will write new entries on the website. In addition, we have also published during this time &lt;a href=&#34;https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/tag/foliar-fertilizers/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;3 papers on foliar fertilisation&lt;/a&gt;, in which some of the chemical compounds that we have obtained as final product in the sulphate carbonation experiments have been used as fertilisers. These articles are also freely available in the publications section of this website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can only say goodbye until the next entry, which I hope to be able to publish soon (because it will mean that we have published one of the two remaining articles).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the French would say, Au revoir!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Concept paper highlighted by editors</title>
      <link>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2023-04-17-editors-spotlights/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2023-04-17-editors-spotlights/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The concept paper we published about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/syst.202300002&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;chemobrionics database&lt;/a&gt; in ChemSystemsChem has been selected by the editors of Chemistry Europe and can now be found in the Editors&#39; Choice: Spotlights section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./screenshot.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We are looking for a trainee</title>
      <link>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2022-10-18-looking-for-a-trainee/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2022-10-18-looking-for-a-trainee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At CARS-CO2 we are looking for a master student (M2) to work for four months on the project starting in February or March 2023. The advertisement as well as all the necessary information on how to apply can be found here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.osug.fr/missions/formations-universitaires/stages/offres-de-stages-master-2/eau-climat-environnement/carbonation-of-sulphate-minerals-for-co2-sequestration.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Carbonation of sulphate minerals for CO2 sequestration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested or have any questions or doubts, please do not hesitate to write to the email listed in the advertisement. We look forward to hearing from you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IMA 2022 conference</title>
      <link>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2022-06-22-ima-2022-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2022-06-22-ima-2022-conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Good news! First results of CARS-CO2 project will be presented at IMA2022 conference in Lyon (France).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk is entitled &lt;strong&gt;Monitoring CaSO4 carbonation with in situ Raman spectroscopy to study CO2 sequestration&lt;/strong&gt; (by &lt;em&gt;Carlos Pimentel&lt;/em&gt;, Germán Montes-Hernández, Alexander E.S. Van Driessche). I will present the results on Wednesday 20th at 12:30 in the session of &lt;em&gt;Mineral-Fluid interactions&lt;/em&gt;. The abstract can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/362179891_Monitoring_CaSO4_carbonation_with_in_situ_Raman_spectroscopy_to_study_CO2_sequestration&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the information about the conference can be found in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ima2022.fr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IMA2022 webpage&lt;/a&gt;. The scientific program can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://ima2022.process.y-congress.com/ScientificProcess/schedule/?setLng=en#&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project abstract</title>
      <link>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2022-02-01-project-abstract/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cpimentelguerra.com/CARS-CO2/post/2022-02-01-project-abstract/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the CARS-CO2 project webpage. If you want to know what the objectives of this project are, you can read the project summary below. The results of the research will be presented in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CARS-CO2 is a multidisciplinary project that is centred on the carbonatation of sulphates to establish a novel route to capture and store atmospheric CO2. The two main objectives of this project are: (i) improve our understanding of the crystallization process of sulphates and carbonates at mild hydrothermal conditions, and (ii) study the mechanism, kinetics and stability of the carbonatation of sulphates. Both objectives are paramount to accomplish our foremost goal, which is to evaluate the potential of sulphate carbonatation as a “sequestrator” of CO2. To achieve this, several state-of-the-art laboratory and synchrotron-based scattering techniques will be used to monitor in situ the mineral formation and transformation reactions. To complement the body of bulk mineralization data, during a secondment, isotopic fingerprinting will be used to determine the role of magnesium in the transformation reaction and to define if the transformation is solid state or solution mediated. The results obtained in this project will not only shed light on how CaSO4-based (waste) materials can help to reduce CO2 in the atmosphere but will also further unveil the formation mechanisms of sulphates and carbonates for relevant environmental conditions on Earth and Mars.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
